<idea-plugin>
    <id>com.codotchi.pycharm-codotchi</id>
    <name>Codotchi</name>
    <version>1.16.0</version>
    <vendor>codotchi</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
<img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dylscoop/vscode_gotchi/main/vscode/media/monkey_adult_1x.png" height="64" alt="Monkey sprite" />
<img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dylscoop/vscode_gotchi/main/vscode/media/dog_adult_1x.png" height="64" alt="Dog sprite" />
<img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/dylscoop/vscode_gotchi/main/vscode/media/snake_adult_1x.png" height="64" alt="Snake sprite" />

<p>Grow and raise your personal virtual pet as a JetBrains plugin while you code.</p>

<h2>Overview</h2>

<p>codotchi is a JetBrains plugin that lets you raise a digital pet inspired by the original Tamagotchi. Your pet
lives in a tool window panel, reacts to your coding activity, and needs regular care to survive and evolve into
its final form. Any support and feedback is much appreciated!</p>

<p>Your pet is drawn from one of <b>14 sprite sets</b>, 12 of which are based on a zodiac animal, assigned to you
at random when you start a new game.</p>

<h2>Features</h2>
<ul>
  <li><b>Tool window pet panel</b> — pixel art pet with animated sprites, stat bars, and action buttons rendered in a JCEF webview</li>
  <li><b>Classic Tamagotchi mechanics</b> — hunger, happiness, discipline, energy, health, weight, and age stats, all decaying in real time</li>
  <li><b>Full care system</b> — feed meals and snacks, play mini-games, put pet to sleep, clean droppings, give medicine, scold and praise</li>
  <li><b>Life cycle &amp; evolution</b> — egg → baby → child → teen → adult → senior, with the final character determined by how well you cared for your pet</li>
  <li><b>Pet customisation</b> — name your pet, choose a pet type, and pick a colour palette on first launch</li>
  <li><b>Sickness &amp; death</b> — neglect your pet and it gets sick; leave it untreated and it dies</li>
  <li><b>OpenCode integration</b> — your pet lives in the terminal too; use /codotchi commands to care for it alongside your AI coding session, with shared state across VS Code, PyCharm, and OpenCode</li>
  <li><b>Status bar integration</b> — pet name and stage always visible in the IDE status bar</li>
  <li><b>Persistent state</b> — pet survives IDE restarts; offline time is accounted for with capped stat decay</li>
  <li><b>Configurable</b> — customise font size, pet size, colours, idle thresholds, attention call behaviour, and more via <b>Settings → Tools → Codotchi</b></li>
</ul>

<h2>Requirements</h2>
<ul>
  <li>JetBrains IDE version <b>2024.1 or later</b> (IntelliJ IDEA, PyCharm, WebStorm, GoLand, Rider, etc.)</li>
  <li>JCEF must be enabled in your IDE (it is on by default in 2024.1+)</li>
</ul>

<h2>Installation</h2>
<p>See the <a href="https://github.com/dylscoop/codotchi">GitHub repository</a> for full installation instructions,
pre-built releases, and the OpenCode integration download.</p>

<h2>Using the plugin</h2>
<p>Once installed and the IDE has restarted:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Click <b>Codotchi</b> in the right-hand tool window bar, or go to <b>View → Tool Windows → Codotchi</b>.</li>
  <li>On first launch the <b>New Codotchi</b> setup screen appears:
    <ul>
      <li>Enter a name (up to 16 characters).</li>
      <li>Choose a <b>pet type</b> — each has different stat decay rates.</li>
      <li>Choose a <b>colour palette</b> — affects the sprite's colour scheme.</li>
      <li>Click <b>Hatch!</b></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Your pet now lives in the tool window. Care for it using the action buttons:
    <b>Feed</b>, <b>Snack</b>, <b>Play</b>, <b>Pat</b>, <b>Sleep</b>, <b>Clean</b>, <b>Medicine</b>,
    <b>Praise</b>, and <b>Scold</b>.</li>
  <li>Your pet's state is saved automatically and restored the next time the IDE opens. Stat decay while the IDE
    is closed is capped at 60% of each maximum so a long break won't instantly kill your pet.</li>
  <li>Your pet's name and current life stage are always visible in the <b>status bar</b> at the bottom of the IDE window.</li>
</ol>

<h2>Actions</h2>
<table>
  <tr><th>Action</th><th>What it does</th></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Feed</b></td><td>Gives your pet a full meal. Restores a large chunk of hunger. Limited to 3 meals per wake cycle — overfeeding past that has no effect.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Snack</b></td><td>Gives a small treat. Boosts happiness instead of hunger, but adds more weight. More than 3 snacks in a row will make your pet sick.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Play</b></td><td>Opens the mini-game picker. Choose Left / Right, Higher or Lower, or Coin Flip. Winning gives +15–25 happiness; losing applies a −5 penalty. Costs 25 energy — your pet can't play if exhausted.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Pat</b></td><td>Gives your pet a gentle pat. Boosts happiness by +10. Costs 20 energy. Accessed via the Play menu. Cannot be used while your pet is sleeping or exhausted.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Sleep</b></td><td>Puts your pet to sleep. Energy slowly regenerates while it sleeps and your pet cannot take any other actions. Wake it manually or wait for full energy.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Clean</b></td><td>Clears all droppings from the screen. Pets produce droppings roughly every 20 minutes. Leaving 3 or more uncleaned will make your pet sick.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Medicine</b></td><td>Treats sickness. Requires 3 doses to fully cure. Restores a small amount of health per dose. Use it as soon as your pet falls ill to prevent health loss.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Praise</b></td><td>Rewards good behaviour. Raises the discipline stat, which contributes to a better care score and a higher-tier evolution.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Scold</b></td><td>Corrects bad behaviour. Also raises discipline. Use it when your pet misbehaves rather than at random, as it has no direct stat benefit beyond discipline.</td></tr>
</table>

<p><b>Tip:</b> keep all four stat bars (Hunger, Happy, Energy, Health) out of the red to maximise your care score,
which determines which character your pet evolves into at each life stage.</p>

<h2>Mini-games</h2>
<p>Clicking <b>Play</b> opens the game picker (requires 25 energy). Three games are available:</p>
<table>
  <tr><th>Game</th><th>How to win</th></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Left / Right</b></td><td>3 rounds. The pet hides behind one of two doors. You have 3 seconds per round to pick the correct door. Win 2 out of 3 rounds to win.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Higher or Lower</b></td><td>5 rounds. A number is shown (1–100). Guess whether the next number will be higher or lower. Get 4 out of 5 correct to win.</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Coin Flip</b></td><td>Call Heads or Tails. A single coin flip decides the outcome.</td></tr>
</table>

<h2>Pet Types</h2>
<table>
  <tr><th>Type</th><th>Tendency</th></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Codeling</b></td><td>Balanced across all stats</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Bytebug</b></td><td>High energy, hunger decays faster</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Pixelpup</b></td><td>High happiness, but happiness decays faster</td></tr>
  <tr><td><b>Shellscript</b></td><td>Slow evolver, high base health</td></tr>
</table>
<p>Each pet animal has its own sprite set.</p>

<hr/>
<p><em>"Grow your best pet by writing your best code."</em></p>
    ]]></description>

    <idea-version since-build="241"/>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">

        <!-- Persistence -->
        <applicationService
            serviceImplementation="com.codotchi.CodotchiPersistence"/>

        <!-- Display settings -->
        <applicationService
            serviceImplementation="com.codotchi.CodotchiSettings"/>

        <!-- Main application service (tick scheduler, state manager) -->
        <applicationService
            serviceImplementation="com.codotchi.CodotchiPlugin"/>

        <!-- Tool window -->
        <toolWindow
            id="Codotchi"
            anchor="right"
            factoryClass="com.codotchi.CodotchiToolWindow"
            icon="/META-INF/codotchi_icon.svg"/>

        <!-- Status bar widget -->
        <statusBarWidgetFactory
            id="CodotchiStatusWidget"
            implementation="com.codotchi.CodotchiStatusWidgetFactory"
            order="last"/>

        <!-- Settings page: Settings > Tools > Codotchi -->
        <applicationConfigurable
            parentId="tools"
            instance="com.codotchi.CodotchiConfigurable"
            id="com.codotchi.CodotchiConfigurable"
            displayName="Codotchi"/>

        <!-- Notification group for attention calls -->
        <notificationGroup
            id="Codotchi Attention Calls"
            displayType="BALLOON"
            isLogByDefault="true"/>

    </extensions>

    <actions>
        <!-- Dev-only sprite preview gallery — visible only when developer mode is active -->
        <action id="com.codotchi.OpenSpritePreview"
                class="com.codotchi.OpenSpritePreviewAction"
                text="Codotchi: Open Sprite Preview (Dev)"
                description="Open the sprite preview gallery (developer mode only)">
            <add-to-group group-id="ToolsMenu" anchor="last"/>
        </action>

        <!-- Refresh button in the Codotchi tool window title bar -->
        <action id="com.codotchi.Refresh"
                class="com.codotchi.CodotchiRefreshAction"
                text="Refresh"
                description="Reload pet state from disk (sync with other open windows)">
            <add-to-group group-id="CodotchiToolWindowToolbar" anchor="first"/>
        </action>

        <!-- Tool window toolbar group (shown in the title bar of the Codotchi panel) -->
        <group id="CodotchiToolWindowToolbar"
               class="com.intellij.openapi.actionSystem.DefaultActionGroup">
            <add-to-group group-id="ToolWindowToolbar" anchor="last"/>
        </group>
    </actions>

    <applicationListeners>
        <listener
            class="com.codotchi.CodotchiAppLifecycleListener"
            topic="com.intellij.ide.AppLifecycleListener"/>
    </applicationListeners>

    <projectListeners>
        <listener
            class="com.codotchi.CodotchiEventsManager"
            topic="com.intellij.openapi.fileEditor.FileDocumentManagerListener"/>
        <listener
            class="com.codotchi.CodotchiTabSwitchListener"
            topic="com.intellij.openapi.fileEditor.FileEditorManagerListener"/>
    </projectListeners>

</idea-plugin>
